Hello friends,
health insurance is an essential part of our lives
and we should have that healthy
insurance, but nowadays
people don't understand its need; people consider it money.
Now, what are its advantages, what are its
disadvantages, and when should we take it, why should we take it? We will
talk about it
in this video. So, quickly subscribe
to our channel so that
you can get notifications of those who make such videos. So
let's start.
[Music]
Now friends, first of all, let's talk about what is
health insurance. Friends, just like
we insure
our vehicles to cover the expenses of our vehicles,
future expenses
because they arise after an accident, similarly
we take health insurance. Whenever we
fall ill or have an accident,
we go to the hospital in that condition
and whatever our expenses are,
health insurance covers all your
expenses, whether they are accident-related or illness-
related, whatever
expenses there are, health insurance covers them. So, that's why
I said that this is a very
important part of your life. It is
very important to do it. It has been seen many times that
people's hard-earned money is wasted.  The income which
these people collect for many years
and due to some disease or some
accident, all that money gets
spent or sometimes they even have to
sell their house due to which all
their life's earnings get lost
but what does health insurance do, by paying
a small amount you get covered for the whole year,
you have to remove it every year,
your coverage becomes yours,
whatever expenses you incur under it, the
company will bear it up to a limit, whatever time
you leave, whatever
cover you take, the company will
cover you up to that limit, however
less will be the cost as per the short term, more will be the cost as per the long term
because when it increases
then you get more diseases, so
you
need more cover but if your front end is less then you
can do it by taking less cover also but it is
necessary for everyone whether they have less cover
or they have more cover because
diseases are unknown to anyone, diseases
can come at any time and if diseases come then
your expenses will also come and if seen in today's date then the
expenses that you have incurred in going to the hospital or in this
Meaning, all the expenses related to the doctor have
increased a lot because what
these
hospitals have done in the name of being a company is that
they have started a kind of loot.
If you go to the first floor, then the
expense of ₹10 is given to you for ₹40 and the
bill for that is given for ₹40. So
this loot is going on in the hospital
but somewhere if you take health
insurance and the thing is covered then
you can save that expense,
you
can put that expense on the company. Now let's talk about
what things does health insurance
cover. Now, for example, if you have an accident, the
insurance covers it or there are
diseases for which you do
not have to be admitted, such diseases are also
covered by health insurance,
but it depends on
what things are given in the plan.
Like I told you
about pregnancy or about OPD, these things should be there
in your plan. When you
take the plan, you  It is not necessary to check whether this
thing is there or not because
normally what happens is that the pregnancy
plans are a little different or
if in the policy you have, if your
pregnancy is covered then after
some time, after 2 years or 3
years, after 4 years, you are
covered for wearing it and even in that a limit is put
like suppose you get Rs. 35000
in normal pregnancy and
you get Rs. 50000 in caesarean pregnancy,
if the child is born through caesarean then
he gets it, it depends on different names of
different
policies and some policies are available for pregnancy also in
which you are
covered for a short time also, so you can check that also,
but
basically what I mean to say is that the
health insurance plan will
cover any kind of accident, any action, any illness occurring in any way, it will
also cover that, for
how long will it cover, meaning there are some exclusions
I will tell you later how it is,
after how many days it will be done, I will tell you later,
but it will cover OPD, day
care treatment, anything like that,
you don't have to be admitted, that
too is covered by you, so these kinds of
diseases or things like this are
covered by health insurance. Now let's talk about
what things we should look for when we take insurance. I have already made this,
we have seen that if someone has a
claim, then we have
also seen that we have to take insurance, but it should be admitted, so that
we end up taking the wrong insurance. The
first thing is the claim response. There are
about 30-35 companies in India
which will provide your health insurance,
but which companies have a good claim response and
which ones have a bad one.
If you go to make a claim and you are
getting the claim within two days, your
response is coming in 48 hours, 72 hours,
then what will you do with such a
insurance? By the time the
response comes in 72 hours, they will have
collected a lot of money from you.  Your
policy should be such or the
company from which you have taken insurance should be
such that its response should be very
fast, like I am talking about HDFC,
Tata AIG,
ICICI Lombard or if we talk about
Care Health Insurance, it
means it takes two to two hours or
some companies even get it in half an hour, that is,
your response comes easily in two to four to five hours and your
approval is done easily. What
happens after approval is that whatever your expenses are, the
hospital takes all those expenses
from the company, they keep adding them to the company's approval,
if the approval does not come then you will have to
deposit it in cash, when the
approval comes in two days, only then they return the
money to you whenever you are discharged, then
you have to be saved from this thing, first of all
you have to look for a company
which is good, now it should not be like there are
some companies like Universal Surplus, that is, a
person may die but they do not get a response, then
such a company is this Chola Mandalam  There is an
Aditya who is filling it, how do they get so many
rejections, I mean
how recently they rejected our dengue case,
which was a very simple case, I
mean you have to stay away from them,
you have to search for such companies,
which company is good, according to me I will
tell you the names of four Panch Rooms, which I
also told you, HDFC, Tata, G Care
Health Insurance,
Star Health Insurance, Tokyo, this
company is good, apart from this there are other companies,
these companies are also good, so
when you take insurance from them, then definitely check this thing,
whose response is so fast,
apart from that let's talk about room and ISO
category, this thing is very important to note
that if you are
taking insurance up to ₹300000 then you
can get a capping, within that by capping I
mean that when you are taking insurance
of ₹300000 then the room category will be
only 1%, you will get normal room category
and 1% will be borne by the company,
now the front order of Rs 3 lakh  I have
taken a cover of ₹300000, one percent of that is Rs.3000,
which room comes in Rs.3000, so as of
today, rooms are available for at least Rs.8000,
Rs.10000, Rs.15000, which are
single private rooms, so we have to try that
in whichever policy we are looking or searching, we have to
check that how much
money the company will pay us for the room, we have to take that policy,
similarly it does it at two percent, 100%
means ₹3 lakh ₹6000, so what will happen in Rs.6000, its
expense can be, it can be Rs.10000, it can be
Rs.20, it can be Rs.30000, so
we will take that policy, as long as we have cover in it, there will be
coverage, so in this thing.  You have to pay attention
and whenever you are taking a policy of 3 lakhs
then definitely check whether there is a cap in it or
not. Otherwise,
you will not get it in the policy of four or five lakhs or more.
In most of the companies, if some plan is
cheaper then it is possible that you may get it but the maximum
capping you will not get is above 5 lakhs. You may get it in the 4 lakh or 3 lakh
or 2 lakh plan. There are
more chances that you will get it. Now
after that let's talk
about pre and post hospice.
Whenever you get admitted, which company is covering the
expenses before admission and after admission for
how many days,
like it covers the above. Suppose you are
admitted for some disease but
its medical test
or checkup is being done for 1 month, then the
company covers them too. Now it is
possible that you are doing it for 2 months in advance, so
how much is the company covering, it will cover the expenses of 30 days before,
60 days after discharge, like it is
long, it covers the expenses of 30 days before
and 60 days after discharge.  It
covers expenses up to but if we talk about the same thing
about the above then it
covers the expenses of 60 days before and after 180 days i.e.
after 6 months,
so this thing is very important because
after discharge
you do not even know for how many days your medicines will last, so the maximum number of days the
post of the
hospital will be for will
matter more, so try to
get maximum number of days,
now let's talk about the fourth number, if you make a TPA
policy then the
claims are passed in two ways, either the company itself will pass it then it will be
considered as an announced claim or the
company will have some companies with it, TPA is a third
party company, the
company will give all the things to it, brother, if you look at this thing, then
first the claim will go to the TPA,
after that the TPA will
pass it, then approval from the company happens many
times, a preliminary claim comes from the company, so
always keep that thing in mind that the in-house claim that
you get is better, it will
go directly to the company, but if it is for TP then
a third party company will be involved in it
What will happen between you and the company in that? First it will go to the
third party, after that
one man will pass it, okay with
approval, then it will go to the company,
approval will come from there, after that they will
pass your claim,
then if you complain to the company then all these
things will be done separately, although it does
not matter, almost all the things are
easily available in claim TV, they are
easily available in these also, but you should
try to get it for in-house, it is
better now, let's talk about
waiting period, while taking a policy, you must
check what is the waiting period for diseases, if
you take a new policy then no
disease is covered for you for 30 days,
only accident will be covered
from the first day, after that the
diseases which will be covered will be after 30 days,
now after 30 days, when will the disease occur, the
list is very long, both those which will be covered
and those which will not be covered, but
I will tell you an idea, whatever can happen to
you suddenly, like you get
fever, cold, hang, malaria
Or you have a heart attack, or if you have had a
heart attack for the first time, these diseases can happen to
you suddenly. This is a
term of 30 days, but some things take
time, like if you have sugar,
diabetes, or any other liver-kidney
related disease,
HIV, or even tea, companies do
not cover them. Some companies may cover them, but
most companies do not. So, such
major diseases like sugar, diabetes,
or
diseases related to eyes, companies
cover them after 2 years. Some companies
cover them after one year, some
companies cover them after 2 years. So,
you have to pay attention to this thing that is being
covered after 30 days, which disease is
not covered after 2 years,
and some diseases like you
already have a claim, if you have any disease before taking the policy, then it
comes under this category. Pre-adjustment disease, if you have any such
disease, then you have to
tell the company about it. When you take the policy, if you
tell them at the time of taking the policy, then the company may
cover it after 2 years.  Take it and it
may be covered after 3 years or 4 years
or it may happen that the company
can also exclude it permanently or
can increase your premium a little,
for that
it will depend on the time at which you
take the policy, so you have to keep this thing in mind that you
must find out the waiting period, how much
waiting period we are getting in which company,
after that let's talk about
which company is cashless in network hospitals, nowadays
you can find all the companies in most of the cities,
but if you live outside the city,
in a rural area, then
you must check this thing whether the
hospitals around you are covered or
not, or if they are covered then how many hospitals are there
and you must take the list of that
after taking the policy because
in case of emergency only that
list will be available to you, so it should
not always happen that when you need it then you
sit asking for the list, you should not do this, so
whenever you are taking a policy from an agent, if you
take a policy from someone, then keep the list in advance
So that in case of emergency,
your needs will be fulfilled.
After that, let's talk about consumers. There are
some things that are
not covered in your policy, which are called
consumer items or non-medical items,
such as your arm charges or
your gloves, food and drink expenses, so
these types of charges are
not covered, so what do you do for this?
Now you can take a rider while taking the policy.
If you are taking a normal policy level later, then
you will have to pay these charges and
these charges can range from ₹1000 to ₹10000,
20000, even 50000, depending on the
case to case, it will
depend on how many consumers have been added for you. According to
me, in fever or
infection cases,
consumer items are more in cases where they are
less in normal cases, so now you have to look into this thing
and you can add a rider by paying some money, say
1500 rupees.  In
which the company also pays your non-medical charges,
so try to
add that to the rate so that whatever
charges you have, now suppose you are
admitted for fever, your cost is ₹200000, if you have to
pay ₹25000 then what will be the benefit,
but if you pay ₹1500 extra
for that then all your
charges are covered and the company will
pay it, so you must check it once.
Now let's talk about co-payment,
what happens many times, you buy policies, there is a
copayment in it, copayment
means that for
8-20 years, the company will pay 80% and you will pay 20%, so there are
some plans like this, it is included
in the copayment or if your
policy is above 60 years of age, meaning
you are already running, you are
60 years old, you reach 61, then
in most of the cases copayment is automatically charged
which is around 20%.
So whenever you have a policy, always check this thing.
Or if you are above 60 years of age
and your policy is in force, then
definitely check whether
any copayment is being charged in your policy.
What happens to the copayment? If your bill is for ₹1 lakh,
then you will have to pay ₹20,000. The
company will pay ₹80,000 and a ratio of ₹820 will be charged.
But here also there is a
writer of payment details. After applying it, you will
cover that and the
company will also pay any copayment. Plus, some plans
which are available cheaply in the market
may still have copayments. So,
definitely check this copayment. If the cost
comes to ₹10 lakh or ₹2 lakh,
then it will be very difficult for you.
Now let's talk
about group policies and individual policies. By
individual policy, I mean the individual policy
of a single person.
I mean the
policy which you are taking from outside.  If you are
taking a group policy from an agent, I mean the one
you get from the company where
you work or if a
bank gives you a credit card company, then it is a
group policy, it may be so, it is
not that all the banks are giving you group policies,
some banks can also give you normal
policies or Indian policies,
advise like
credit cards are also given by the company, so
most of the policies give this group policy
and what is the harm to you,
in normal policies you can port the company,
if you take it, for example, you
can port from Vodafone to Airtel or
from Jio to Vodafone, similarly
you can also switch the health insurance company,
suppose you took insurance from Star Health
Insurance, you
started it two years ago, you did not like it,
you feel that it is not doing well, then
you can shift, here you can
shift to HDFC EGO, but
if you have taken a group policy, the group
policy which you get from the credit card people
or the company which
you are getting the policy from where you are working,
it is from there  If you get a policy, you
cannot port it, so
always keep this in mind that you will get it only if you continue from there.
Suppose if you leave the job, it will expire, you will have to take the
policy again and
all the exclusions in that policy, there is a
waiting period of 2 years, there is a waiting period of 4 years, that will have to be
applied again. Similarly,
avoid the group policies of credit cards or the group policies of banks, do not take them because there
is no option to switch there,
you cannot think of it, it is possible that
in the beginning you may get
more facilities in the group policies, it is an
individual normal policy, but
in future, if you have
taken a policy outside the agent or you have
purchased the policy from some website,
you will
get more benefits from the policy there, in future,
you have to save these group policies,
you should not take a group policy, if you get it from the company then
take it because you will have to
take advice from there, if it is
possible then skip from there and take
your own policy.  Take this, which will be useful for you
in the future,
so before moving ahead,
subscribe because
you will get notifications for such videos and we will make
good videos for you, so let's talk about
restoration, there is a feature
of issue within the policy, whatever is your
time limit
and if you spend ₹500000
on any illness, then that policy gets registered by you and
again 5 lakh
rupees are added to it, now in many plans, it
can also be taken for illness, if you can take it
for illness then it will depend on the
top plan, if you are
taking a plan from the top which is in the name of Rear Show, then in that
you will get the
benefit of restoration
for illness also, but if you are taking it from Care then you will
get the benefit for illness in it, meaning
someone in your family gets admitted or like
you have taken a claim on us, in that you get
some other claim except mine, then you have to
check this thing, if you get restoration
and if you
get it for illness then it is better,
after that we will talk about Nokli Mall,
also keep this in mind  Keep in mind that if you are employed and you are
not claiming, since we have been running this policy for the past
four years and have
not claimed, then you should
get some extra benefit. So, we need to see
which Nokul benefits you are getting. Mostly, for
example, in Manipal side, you get 5%
annually, but it does not reduce upon making a claim. You
get 10% in care, but if you hire a writer, you
also get 60% in care. You
get 20% for automatic. So, it depends on
how much you get on the plan.
But try to get at least 10-20%.
10% or 20%, so that if you do
not make a claim, your cover increases. And when
you make a claim for the first time, the entire
coverage with the fake mall will be
reduced to you in one go.
Apart from that, let's talk about some other
benefits that you can avail, such as
home care. If you cannot get admitted, the
hospital doctor will
come to your home and take care of you.  You can pay the debt or if there is an
ambulance expense, how much is this
company spending on it
or consider
how much medical checkup you are getting, some
companies provide medical checkup from the first year,
some companies
provide medical checkup after 2 years, so you have to
see how many times you are getting medical checkup in a year,
so there are some
small benefits like this, you can also avail from it, you take
insurance, so
whenever you take a policy, you have to
check everything properly, you have to
check the details of what is being provided in the policy, do
not take whatever the agenda
says, you have to do this, whatever
policy you are taking, you have to pay a little
attention, there is a little information in it, you have to
read it and find out about it, you have to
check the claim ratio of the company,
how many claims the company is paying, if its
claim is 95%, 96% or even 90% then it is good, if it is
less than that then it means a little bad,
meaning your claims  There is a high chance of getting stuck,
so you have to pay attention to this thing and
you must definitely get health insurance, you have to do this
because if you don't do this
then everything is useless and there is
no telling what will happen in the future,
if you keep working your whole life and one
day it happens that due to some disease you spend all
your money, then everything gets
ruined, so you have to get health
insurance and you must get it, and you have to
tell other people about it along with yourself, what are its benefits,
why should you get it, so what will happen is that
people will get a little awareness, people will
know a little about it and then they will move forward for health
insurance, so
how did you like our video,
if there is anything left, then we will try to
tell you in the next video, and if
you want to ask something about what has been told
or want to give us any opinion by commenting, then you
can tell us that,
subscribe to our channel
so that you get notifications of such videos that we make,
thank you